Finding aid to the Margaret Sanger Research Bureau records SSC.MS.00320
Sophia Smith Collection
Margaret Sanger Research Bureau records
1815-1980
1917-1969
Sophia Smith Collection
Margaret Sanger Research Bureau
SSC.MS.00320
11.208 linear feet (22 containers)
The Margaret Sanger Research Bureau (MSRB) operated under numerous names and parent organizations from 1923 to 1974, providing birth control and infertility clicnical services to thousands of patients, and serving as a site for medical research and education on these topics. The MSRB records contain correspondence, printed material, clippings, books, glass slides, films, and a library of 59 books on birth control, sexuality, marriage, family, and related topics. Of particular interest are 19th and 20th century pamphlets on birth control, religious views, sex education, methods and early commercial catalogs; writings by and about Margaret Sanger and other pioneers of the birth control movement; and printed material produced by various birth control leagues and clinics in the United States and England.
Biographical / Historical
The Margaret Sanger Research Bureau (MSRB) operated under numerous names and parent organizations from 1923 to 1974, providing birth control and infertility clicnical services to thousands of patients, and serving as a site for medical research and education on these topics.
Margaret Sanger founded the MSRB in 1923 as the Clinical Research Bureau, operating under the direction of the American Birth Control League (ABCL). In 1928, Sanger resigned as president of the ABCL and assumed full control of the clinic, renaming it the Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau (BCCRB). The BCCRB and the ABCL merged in 1939 and became the Birth Control Federation of America (it became Planned Parenthood Federation of America (PPFA) in 1942 with the clinic retaining much of its, independence. In 1940, it was renamed the MSRB in honor of its founder.
Under the guidelines of the 1939 merger, the MSRB was only loosely affiliated with PPFA until the mid-1950s, when budget deficits forced the Bureau to more closely align its services with the Federation in exchange for financial assistance. The Bureau assisted with fund-raising and became the clinical research arm of the PPFA. In return PPFA funded the Bureau and provided grants for doctors and researchers on the Bureau staff.
In 1968, because of continuing financial difficulties the Bureau became affiliated with Columbia University. However, budgetary difficulties in 1974 forced the Bureau to shut down and combine its staff with Planned Parenthood of New York City in a new facility called the Margaret Sanger Center in New York.
Between 1940 and 1962 (the last year of Sanger's involvement with the MSRB) the Bureau provided comprehensive contraceptive services for women and couples, and became the largest combined birth control and fertility center in the world.
After Medical Director Hannah Stone's death in 1941, Abraham Stone, her husband and successor, altered and expanded the MSRB to accommodate his growing interest in infertility. In 1945, Stone inaugurated a Fertility Service that offered counseling, testing, and treatment for infertile couples. He expanded the Bureau's Marriage Consultation Service and steered the Research Department into a greater emphasis on infertility studies. While the Bureau continued to offer contraceptive services, the number of patients dropped as contraception became more widely available through private physicians. However, the Bureau grew as a teaching center, offering seminars, research projects and clinical work for visiting doctors, nurses, and medical students. The Bureau also offered a fellowship program for gynecologists and obstetricians for intensive training in birth control techniques.
Margaret Sanger withdrew from day-to-day MSRB affairs in the 1940s, but continued to make many of the budgetary and personnel decisions. Though she disagreed with how the Clinic had evolved under Abraham Stone's leadership, she continued to raise funds for the MSRB. In 1950 Sanger turned over even more control to Stone, naming him director and selling him the West 16th Street building. For more information on the Margaret Sanger Research Bureau see the Margaret Sanger Papers Project.
Scope and Contents
The Margaret Sanger Research Bureau records contain correspondence, clippings, pamphlets (some in foreign languages), miscellaneous printed material, books, and 194 glass slides and two films used by Norman Hines for lectures on birth control in the 1930s.
It appears that these records contain items from the Bureau's library as well as remaining historical material from its consolidation in 1974. The collection is less the administrative records of the Bureau, although there are a few, and more subject files collected by the Bureau over the years. The Margaret Sanger papers include more records from the Bureau. Nevertheless this collection represents a rich source of information on the early birth control movement in the U.S. and abroad. Of particular interest are general 19th and 20th century pamphlets on birth control, religious views, sex education, contraceptive methods (dating from 1877), and early commercial catalogs; writings by Margaret Sanger and other pioneers of the early birth control movement such as suffragist and socialist Annie Besant; birth control and sex education advocates Mary Ware Dennett and Marie Stopes; Malthusians George Drysdale, Charles Robert Drysdale, and Charles Vickery Drysdale; and eugenicist, socialist, and feminist Moses Harmon. Organization files include reports, history, bibliographies, laws, legislation, and general literature published by the American Birth Control League, Birth Control Federation of America, National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control, National Committee on Maternal Health, Planned Parenthood Federation of America and other birth control leagues, clinics and conferences in the United States and England. The collection includes a library of 59 books on birth control, sexuality, marriage, family, and related topics.
The collection also includes several accessions of materials received in recent years, including donations of materials belonging to the MSRB's last director, Dr. Aquiles J. Sobrero.
Related Material
Associated material in the Margaret Sanger Papers and the Planned Parenthood Federation of America Records, Sophia Smith Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
A letter from the Margaret Sanger Center written in 1974 indicates that "historical material on Margaret Sanger and the birth control movement which has been housed for many years at the Margaret Sanger Research Bureau" was donated to the Sophia Smith Collection. Margaret Sanger Research Bureau material was also received in 1967 and it is presumed that most or all of it was placed in the Margaret Sanger papers and records of the Planned Parenthood Federation of America.
The accessions of materials from Aquiles Sobrero were donated separately by Adela and Raul Sobrero in 2016 and 2017.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection received before 2005 are arranged into series by type of material. Materials received since 2005 have been added to the end of the collection as one new series for each accession.
Birth control--Great Britain--History; Birth control--Law and legislation--United States--History--Sources; Birth control--Religious aspects--Catholic Church; Birth control--Research--History--Sources; Birth control--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Birth control clinics--United States--History--Sources Contraceptives--Research--Sources; Hygiene, Sexual--History--20th century--Sources; Marriage--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Sex instruction--United States--History; Women--Health and hygiene--United States--20th century--Sources; articles; Books; Brochures; Catalogs; clippings; correspondence; Manuscripts; Motion pictures; Pamphlets; reports; Slides; photographs; Blossom, F.A. (Frederick Augustus), b. 1878; Dennett, Mary Ware, 1872-1947; Drysdale, George, 1825-1904; Ellis, Havelock, 1859-1939; Harmon, Moses, 1830-1910; Stone, Abraham, 1890-; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966; Stopes, Marie Carmichael, 1880-1958; Stone, Hannah M. (Hannah Mayer), 1894-1941; American Birth Control League; Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau (New York, N.Y.); Birth Control Federation of America; Malthusian League; Margaret Sanger Research Bureau; National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control; National Committee on Maternal Health; Planned Parenthood Federation of America; Sobrero, Aquiles J.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS, 1886-1973
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains printed material, correspondence, writings, and notes by and about nineteen people, most of whom were birth control pioneers from the late 19th and early 20th centuries. They are arranged in alphabetical order. Of particular interest are pamphlets by suffragist and socialist Annie Besant; birth control and sex education advocates Mary Ware Dennett and Marie Stopes; Malthusians George Drysdale, Charles Robert Drysdale, and Charles Vickery Drysdale; and eugenicist, socialist, and feminist Moses Harmon.
  There is a significant amount of biographical material on Margaret Sanger including obituaries and clippings. An article she wrote for Reader's Digest in 1951, along with letters women wrote in response are included. Many of the women ask specific questions about birth control. Also of interest are various editions (both in English and other languages) of Sanger's Family Limitation beginning in 1914. There are also copies of Sanger's Women and the New Race, Magnetation Methods of Birth Control; Birth Control Through the Ages; Women, Morality and Birth Control; and Voluntary Motherhood. (There are also writings by Sanger in SERIES VI. BOOKS) William Sanger's The Trial of William Sanger, September 10, 1915, regarding his arrest and trial for handing out birth control literature is also included.
  There is a large amount of manuscript material by Abraham Stone including a copy of Birth Control (n.d.), proof and typed copies of A Marriage Manual (1968) which he wrote with his wife Hannah, and his Psychosomatic Factors in Marriage (1946).
  - Besant, Annie, 1886; 1889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Blossom, Frederick, 1913-23; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dennett, Mary Ware, 1928-29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Drysdale, George, Charles Robert and Charles Vickery, 1901; 1929-51; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    General
    [see also SERIES II. ORGANIZATION FILES -Great Britain - Malthusian League and SERIES V. BOOKS]
  - Ellis, Havelock, 1925-26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    [see also SERIES V. BOOKS]
  - Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley (Box 1)
    [see Blossom, Frederick]
  - Goldman, Emma, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hanau, Stella, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Harmon, Moses, 1907-10; undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hepburn, Katherine Houghton, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Himes, Norman, 1931-1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    [see also SERIES V. BOOKS and OVERSIZED MATERIALS]
  - Knowlton, Charles, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Newman, Elizabeth, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sanger, Margaret (Box 1)
    - Articles, clippings, and printed material, 1928-73; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Obituaries and tributes, 1929; 1966-73; undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Readers Digest article and related correspondence, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Writings (Box 2)
      - Family Limitation (Box 2)
        - English editons, 1914-24; undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - Foreign language editions, 1915-17; undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1920-60; undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sanger, William, 1917; undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Shane, Dr., undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Stone, Abraham (Box 3)
    - Birth Control: ms. copy, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - A Marriage Manual (with Hannah Stone), 1968 edition (Box 3)
      - Proof copy (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Typed copy, undated (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
    - Psychosomatic Factors in Marriage, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Stone, Hannah, 1925-37 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Stopes, Marie, 1921-36; undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Vickery, Alice, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    [see also SERIES II. ORGANIZATION FILES - Great Britain - Malthusian League]
  - Zeublin, Charles, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- SERIES II. ORGANIZATION FILES, 1885-1972
  This series is divided into two subseries: Great Britain and United States. Each is arranged alphabetically. The first subseries contains information on twenty birth control organizations, clinics, and related groups in Great Britain including Scotland and India. Of particular interest are pamphlets and printed material of the Malthusian League (1911-51).
  The second subseries contains information on thirty-four US organizations and clinics. The primary organizations represented are the American Birth Control League (ABCL) (1922-39), the Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau (BCCRB) (1939-40), and the National Committee on the Federal Legislation for Birth Control (NCFLBC) (1929-36). The ABCL records include annual meeting materials, clinic data, history, publications related to laws and legislation, and birth control literature. The BCCRB material contains annual reports and meeting material, newsletters, clinic information, and miscellaneous pamphlets and printed material. The NCFLBC also contains newsletters, news releases, pamphlets, and printed material. There is one folder on the Margaret Sanger Research Bureau (1927-29) which contains a history of birth control and of the MSRB as well as a study on contraception and menopause. Worthy of note in this subseries is a copy of a flyer in three languages from Sanger's Brooklyn clinic (46 Amboy St.) and flyers from her Harlem clinic.
  - Great Britain (Box 4)
    [See also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS - Stopes, Marie; Himes, Norman]
    - Birmingham Women's Welfare Centre, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Birth Control International Information Centre, 1935; undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Contraceptive Trade Association, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - East Street Welfare Centre, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Family Planning Association, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Glasgow Women's Welfare and Advisory Clinic, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - International Medical Group for the Investigation of Birth Control, 1929; undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Madras Neo Malthusian League, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Malthusian League (Box 4)
      - Pamphlets, 1911-21 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Miscellaneous printed material, 1885-1951; undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Maternity and Child Welfare Centres, 1929-30 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Mother's Clinic, 1933-38; undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - National Birth Control Association, 1937-38 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - New Generation League, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - North Kensington Women's Welfare Center, 1924-56; undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Sex Education Society, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Society and Clinic for Constructive Birth Control, 1931; undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Society for the Provision of Birth Control Clinics, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Wives' Clinic for Discretionary Birth Control, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Women's Welfare Clinic, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Workers Birth Control Group, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - United States (Box 4)
    - American Birth Control League (Box 4)
      - Aims/principles, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Annual meetings, 1929-33 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Clinical Research Department, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Clinics, 1934-38; undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - History, constitution, and miscellaneous reports, 1923-28; undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Laws and legislation, 1926-38; undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Literature catalogs, 1934-39; undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Maternity Research Council, 1923-25 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Publications and printed material, 1922-36; undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau (Box 5)
      - Annual reports, 1939-40 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Annual meetings, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - "The Bulletin,", 1940 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Clinics, 1941; undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Newsletters, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Pamphlets and miscellaneous printed material, 1938-41; undated (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
    - Birth Control League of Massachusetts, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Brooklyn (46 Amboy St.) Birth Control Clinic, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Bureau For Contraceptive Advice, 1929-33 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Citizen's Committee for Planned Parenthood, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Committee of One Hundred, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Committee on Maternal Health (Cincinnati), 1932 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Committee on Maternal Health (NY), 1927-30; undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Harlem Birth Control Clinic, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Illinois Birth Control League, 1924-26 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - International Planned Parenthood Committee, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Margaret Sanger Research Bureau, 1927; 1929; undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Maternal Health Association (Cleveland), 1935 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Maternal Health Center (Newark, NJ), 1924 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Maternal Health Society of Easton (PA), 1932 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Maternal Health League of Michigan, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Minnesota Birth Control League, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Mothers Clinic of Detroit, 1927-31 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Mother's Health Center, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Mountain Maternal Health League of Kentucky, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - National Committee for Planned Parenthood, 1941; undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control (Box 6)
      - Newsletters and news releases, 1929-35 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Pamphlets and miscellaneous printed material, 1929-36; undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - National Committee on Maternal Health, 1932-49 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - National Medical Council on Birth Control, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Palama Settlement (Honolulu), 1938 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Pennsylvania Birth Control Federation, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Planned Parenthood Campaign, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Planned Parenthood Federation of America, 1948; 1953; 1972 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Planned Parenthood of Rochester, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Planned Parenthood of South East Pennsylvania, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Voluntary Parenthood League, 1921; undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - World Population Emergency Campaign, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- SERIES III. CONFERENCES, 1921-1936
  This series contain reports, notes, publications, and miscellaneous printed material on nine conferences held in the United State and abroad. They are arranged alphabetically. Of particular interest is The Practice of Contraception edited by Margaret Sanger and Hannah Stone (from the 7th International Birth Control Conference), reports of the fifth (1922) and sixth (1925) International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference and Birth Control: What It Is, How It Works And What It Will Do from the First American Birth Control Conference, 1921.
  - American Birth Control Conference (First), 1921 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - American Conference on Birth Control and National Recovery (Box 6)
    [see SERIES II. ORGANIZATION FILES - National Council for Federal Legislation for Birth Control]
  - Berlin Sexual Research Congress, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Conference on Birth Control in Asia, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Conference on Contraceptive Research and Clinical Practice, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Conference on the Giving of Information on Birth Control by Health Authorities, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - International Birth Control Conference (Seventh), 1930 (Box 7)
    - The Practice of Contraception: An International Symposium and Survey Edited by Margaret Sanger and Hannah Stone, Baltimore, Williams and Wilkins, 1931 (Box 7)
    - Questionnaire for all workers in birth control Clinics in Europe and the United States (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference (Box 7)
    [see also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS - Stone, Hannah]
    - Fifth, 1922 (Box 7)
      - Report, edited by Raymond Pierpont. London, William Heineman (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Sixth, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - National Birth Control Conference, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - World Population Conference, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- SERIES IV. SUBJECT FILES, 1873-1962
  This series is divided in two subseries: Birth Control and Sex Education. Birth Control is divided into eight sections: anti-birth control; clinics; laws, legislation, and trials; marriage and birth control; medical views; contraceptive methods; religious views; and miscellaneous. Law, legislation, and trials contains information on the Comstock law which forbade the sending of birth control information through the mail (1873-1915); New York vs. Margaret Sanger and Ethel Byrne, the trial for opening Sanger's birth control clinic in Brooklyn (1916-29); and US vs. One Package which was a case related to the interception by customs of a package of contraceptives supplies sent to Sanger from Japan (1936). The methods sections contains pamphlets as early as 1877 and of particular interest are early commercial catalogs from drug companies and manufacturers of birth control devices and rubber goods. Miscellaneous pamphlets contains English and foreign language publications.
  - Birth control (Box 7)
    - Anti-birth control, 1889-1931; undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Clinics, 1925-39; undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
      [see SERIES II. ORGANIZATION FILES - Margaret Sanger Research Bureau, Planned Parenthood Federation of America]
    - Clippings, 1929-62; undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Law, legislation, and trials (Box 8)
      [see also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS - Dennett, Mary Ware, Ellis, Havelock, Sanger, William and SERIES II. ORGANIZATION FILES - American Birth Control League, Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau, National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control]
      - Comstock Law, 1873; 1879; 1915 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Federal Trade Commission, 1936-37 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Great Britain, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - New York vs. Margaret Sanger, Ethel Byrne and Fannie Mindell, 1916; 1929 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - U.S. vs One Package, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous pamphlets and printed material, 1930-62; undated (Box 8, Folder 9-10)
    - Marriage and birth control, 1902-31; undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Medical views, 1916-37; undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
      [See also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS - Drysdale, Charles Robert and SERIES II. ORGANIZATION FILES - American Birth Control League - Publications and printed material]
    - Methods (Box 9)
      - Commercial catalogs and flyers, 1926; undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Pamphlets and printed material, 1877-1952; undated (Box 10, Folder 2-4)
    - Religious views, 1904-37 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets and printed material (Box 10)
      - English, 1886-1940; undated (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
      - Foreign language, 1908-52; undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Eugenics (Box 11)
    [see SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS - Ellis, Havelock]
  - Sex education, 1919-28 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    [see also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS - Stopes, Marie and SERIES II. ORGANIZATION FILES - Great Britain - Sex Education Society]
- SERIES V. BOOKS, 1901-1951